Frank Whittemore Abrams Papers
Frank Whittemore Abrams Papers
1929-1964
Abrams, Frank W. (Frank Whittemore), 1889-1976
2 linear ft.
Papers of the American executive. Abrams graduated from Syracuse University (Engineering) in 1912, shortly thereafter joined Standard Oil of New Jersey where he served as Director (1940) and Chairman of the Board (1946-1954). Papers include correspondence (1953-1961); a transcript of recorded reminiscences of Abrams by the Columbia University Oral History Project Office; photographs; and published materials, including articles by and about Abrams, clippings, and printed speeches.
149313
Biographical History
Frank Whittemore Abrams (1889-1976) was an American businessman and a trustee of Syracuse University.
Abrams was born in Rockville Center, Long Island on June 24, 1889. He attended public schools and graduated from Syracuse University (SU) in 1912. Abrams was married three years later to the former Ruth Florence Corrigan, with whom he had one son. After completing an engineering degree at SU, Abrams was hired by the Standard Oil Company of New Jersey. He worked his way up in the company, becoming superintendent of a plant in 1920, manager of the New York City plants in 1922, director of the company's operations in New York and New Jersey in 1927, and president of the firm in 1933. He served as a director of Standard Oil of New Jersey from 1940 on, and as chairman of the board from 1946 until his retirement in 1954. Abrams was no less active following his retirement, however. Former President Herbert Hoover asked him to be a member of a commission considering reorganization of the executive branch of government.
Abrams served as trustee of several colleges, including Cooper Union and Syracuse University. He was especially interested in the problem of financial aid, and served on the Council for Aid to Higher Education. He also made numerous speeches to business organizations on the subject, saying that support of education was "everybody's business."
Abrams also taught courses in business at Stetson University in Florida, and served on the boards of the Alfred Sloan Foundation, the Ford Foundation, and Industrial Relations Counselors, Inc.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Frank W. Abrams Papers consists of Correspondence, Subject files, Writings, and Published material.
Correspondence contains both incoming and outgoing letters, filed together.
Subject files contains photographs of Abrams.
Writings contains manuscripts of various pieces of writings by Abrams, including a memoir of a European trip taken in 1948 and a transcript of an interview of Abrams done by the Columbia University Oral History Research Office.
Published material includes annual meetings of Standard Oil Company of New Jersey, articles about and by Abrams, printed speeches, clippings, and a copy of court testimony in A. P. Smith Co. v Barlow.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence and published material are arranged alphabetically. Writings are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; Abrams, Frank W. (Frank Whittemore), 1889-1976.; Standard Oil Company of New Jersey.; Business.; Engineers -- United States.; Executives -- United States.; Oil industries.; Petroleum industry and trade.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Interviews.; Manuscripts for publication.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Engineers.; Executives.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Frank Abrams, 1967, 1971.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - A, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Advertising Council, 1959; mentions speech, "Education is Everybody's Business" (Box 1)
  - Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, 1969 (Box 1)
  - American Association of Fund Raising Counsel, 1955 (Box 1)
  - American Petroleum Institute Quarterly, 1956-1957; includes articles (Box 1)
  - B, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - C, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Center for Religion and Society, SUNY Stony Brook, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Christian Science Monitor, 1954-1956; article (Box 1)
  - Columbia University, 1954-1955; 1965 (Box 1)
  - Council for Financial Aid to Education, Inc., 1954; 1956,; 1964,; 1967,; 1969 (Box 1)
  - Council for State University Colleges of Medicine, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - D, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - E, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Economic Club, Detroit, 1956; regarding a speech (Box 1)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight, 1958; Defense Department reorganization (Box 1)
  - F, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Food and Drug Citizens Advisory Committee, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Foreign Policy Association, 1955 (Box 1)
  - G, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - H, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Harper's Magazine, 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Honorary degrees, 1946; 1953-1960 (Box 1)
  - Hoover Commission on Organization of the Executive Branch of Government, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1955; 1964; includes both father and son (Sr. and Jr.) (Box 1)
  - I, miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Industrial Relations Counselors, Inc., 1952-1961 (Box 1)
  - Invitations, speaking invitations, guest invitations, etc.
    - Carleton College, 1958-1959 (Box 1)
    - Case Institute of Technology, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Columbia University, 1957-1959; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Commission for Study of Industrial Medicine, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Desk and Derrick Club, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Eisenhower, American Heritage Foundation, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Elmira College, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Empire State Foundation, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Grand Rapids (Michigan) Chamber of Commerce, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Maryland colleges, 1958 (Box 1)
    - National Fund for Medical Education, 1958; award (Box 1)
    - Newark Rotary Club, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Oil Progress Week luncheon, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Princeton University, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Roper Public Opinion Research Center, Williams College, 1959 (Box 1)
    - St. John's University, 1954 (Box 1)
    - A. P. Sloan Foundation Symposium on Basic Research, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Stetson University, 1958 (Box 1)
    - University of Pennsylvania Council for Financial Aid to Education, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Wabash College, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Wake Forest College, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - World's Fair Trade Center project, 1959 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1954-1966; 7 folders (Box 2)
  - J, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Javits, Jacob, 1957-1958 (Box 2)
  - K, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Kefauver, Estes, 1956 (Box 2)
  - L, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - M, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Mayor's Advisory Council, 1953-1955 (Box 2)
  - N, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - National Commission for Adult Literacy, 1956-1958 (Box 2)
  - New York Herald Tribune, regarding article (Box 2)
  - New York University, 1957; regarding speech, President's Committee for Education Beyond the High School (Box 2)
  - New York University, Bellevue Medical Center, 1947; 1957 (Box 2)
  - O, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - P, miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Planned Parenthood, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Population Reference Bureau, 1961-1966; 1968-1969 (Box 3)
  - R, miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson, 1959 (Box 3)
  - S-T, miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Saturday Review, 1954; 1956,; 1959-1960,; 1962,; 1966; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Stetson University (Florida), 1956-1957; 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - U-W, miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Wallace, DeWitt, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
  - Yale University, 1954 (Box 3)
- Manuscripts
  - 55th Reunion, Class of 1912, Syracuse University, 1967; typescript (Box 3)
  - European trip, 1948; typescript (Box 3)
  - Talks and remarks, 1966; photocopies (Box 3)
  - Transcript of recorded conversation with Abrams, made by Columbia University Oral History Research Office, 1954; typescript (Box 3)
- Published material
  - Address, 1964 (Box 3)
  - Annual meetings, Standard Oil of New Jersey, 1948; 1951-1953,; 1964; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Articles about Abrams, 1940; 1946-1949,; 1951,; 1953,; 1955,; 1961,; 1969; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Articles by Abrams (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings about (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings by (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings scrapbook pages (Box 3)
  - Speeches, 1947-1948; 1950,; 1954-1958,; 1962-1964; typescripts; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Speeches, 1929; 1947-1953,; 1955,; 1959-1960,; 1962,; undated; pamphlets; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Testimony by Abrams, A. P. Smith Co. v Barlow, 1953 (Box 4)
- Subject files
  - Employment of college alumni, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Photographs of Abrams (Box 4)